can you give an example of a bi
remediation project that you were
involved in and how well we have a whole
group of projects that we have been
involved in and we're all are involved
in now but the pedestal species is
moisture mushrooms and moisture
mushrooms break down they grow and every
ecosystem where there's trees in the
world they're virtually everywhere and
they have the amazing ability of not
only digesting wood but but paper
products coffee grounds corn cobs I mean
there isn't a vegetable material or
plant material I haven't found that
Wester mushrooms doesn't like they're
really robust in their enzyme suites and
they can they're very good at breaking
down hydrocarbons and oil so we have
several projects and breaking down
hydrocarbons in Washington State we're
using a sheet mulch of my selenium and
many permaculture people use cardboard
for mulching and they mulch so they're
growing these nice little mats anyhow so
if people are thinking well I've seen my
ceiling underneath my cardboard my mulch
they're actively involved right now they
didn't know it
but perhaps but they're actually growing
these mycelial mats we then choose the
species that we know that its most
powerful against the toxin of concern
and so we have target specificity
factors of a species of a fungus against
a toxin
now oyster mushrooms and turkey tail
mushrooms also break down dioxins
dioxins often come from PCBs which I
uses insulation the fluids around
transformers and dioxins also are a
consequence of Agent Orange which was a
defoliant herbicide and so dioxins are
toxic at parts-per-billion than the most
toxic substances in nature and so the
fact that these fungi can break down
toxins they're otherwise we're
calcitriol which means that they're hard
to break down the fact that can do it so
quickly that leads to habitat
restoration quite nicely and your nature
is has the good thing about micro
diversity is enough species within the
eCos
them that there is a toxic waste
environment nature through natural
selection those species will survive and
begin to work upon it so one of the best
ways of finding this right species for
the remediating the toxic environment
that a permaculture or a group or
anybody else is encountering is go to
that toxic environment doing the
mushroom season Nature has already
selected the ones that are tolerant
there are adaptive and then you test
them to see if they're actually breaking
down the toxins or just tolerant to the
toxins when you find when it's tolerant
and breaking down the toxins you've got
your candidate species oyster mushrooms
by far the easiest